<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE issues SYSTEM "native.dtd">
<issues><issue current="false" identification="title" public_id="" published="true"><id type="doi">10.11646/zootaxa.1103.1</id><title locale="en_US">22 Dec. 2005</title><volume>1103</volume><number>1</number><year>2005</year><date_published>2005-12-22</date_published><section><title locale="en_US">Articles</title><article language="en"><title locale="en_US">Male description and generic review of Agyrtolasia Szymczakowski, with key to genera of Agyrtodini (Coleoptera : Leiodidae : Camiarinae : Agyrtodini)</title><abstract locale="en_US">The male of Agyrtolasia calliptera Szymczakowski is described and new collecting records are provided. The range and habitat of Agyrtolasia resemble those of Australian Agyrtodes Portevin, with A. calliptera found in fungus and forest leaf litter from New South Wales to Southeast Queensland. Pertinent diagnostic and systematic characters are discussed for adult Agyrtodini. The probable phylogenetic placement of Agyrtolasia is very close to Agyrtodes; adult morphology suggests the former is either within or sister to the latter. An illustrated key to world agyrtodine genera is provided.</abstract><indexing><discipline locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></discipline><subject locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></subject><subject_class locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></subject_class></indexing><author primary_contact="true"><firstname>A E</firstname><lastname>Seago</lastname><email><![CDATA[]]></email></author><pages>1-15</pages><date_published>2005-12-22</date_published></article><article language="en"><title locale="en_US">Description of a new species, records of five previously unrecorded species, and rediscovery of a lost species in the genus Ancylis Hubner (Lepidoptera : Tortricidae) from China</title><abstract locale="en_US">We describe and illustrate Ancylis youmiae, sp. nov., from Heilongjiang (Laoyeling), China, and report five other species of Ancylis from China for the first time: A. melanostigma Kuznetsov, 1970, A. partitana (Christoph, 1881), A. repandana Kennel, 1901, A. uncella ([Denis &amp; Schiffermuller], 1775), and A. upupana ( Treitschke, 1835). Ancylis mandarinana (Walsingham, 1900), which has not been documented from China since its original description, is rediscovered. For all species we provide redescriptions, illustrations, and information on geographic distribution and host plants.</abstract><indexing><discipline locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></discipline><subject locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></subject><subject_class locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></subject_class></indexing><author primary_contact="true"><firstname>B K</firstname><lastname>Byun</lastname><email><![CDATA[]]></email></author><author primary_contact="false"><firstname>S C</firstname><lastname>Yan</lastname><email><![CDATA[]]></email></author><pages>17-26</pages><date_published>2005-12-22</date_published></article><article language="en"><title locale="en_US">Two new species of the feather mite genus Dicrurobius Mironov, 2001 (Acari : Astigmata : Pteronyssidae) from drongos (Passeriformes : Dicruridae) in Africa</title><abstract locale="en_US">Two new species of the feather mite genus Dicrurobius Mironov, 2001 are described from drongos ( Passeriformes: Dicruridae) in Africa: Dicrurobius alatus sp. n. from Dicrurus atripennis Swainson, 1837 and D. cameroonensis sp. n. from Dicrurus adsimilis (Bechstein, 1794). New data on host associations and distribution of the sole formerly known species, D. monacrotrichus (Gaud, 1952), are given. A key to three Dicrurobius species known to date is presented.</abstract><indexing><discipline locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></discipline><subject locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></subject><subject_class locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></subject_class></indexing><author primary_contact="true"><firstname>S V</firstname><lastname>Mironov</lastname><email><![CDATA[]]></email></author><author primary_contact="false"><firstname>G</firstname><lastname>Wauthy</lastname><email><![CDATA[]]></email></author><pages>27-39</pages><date_published>2005-12-22</date_published></article><article language="en"><title locale="en_US">Molecular phylogeny of some genera of Pamphagidae (Acridoidea, Orthoptera) from China based on mitochondrial 16S rDNA sequences</title><abstract locale="en_US">Based on the mitochondrial 16S ribosomal DNA partial sequences (473 bp) of 9 species of Pamphagidae (Acridoidea, Orthoptera) from China and of 4 species of Pamphagidae and 2 species of Pyrgomorphidae and Acrididae (as outgroups) retrieved from GenBank, we constructed the molecular phylogeny using the Neighbor Joining (NJ) and Minimum Evolution ( ME) methods based on the nucleotide Kimura 2-parameter model. The results of our study shown that: 1) the ranges of the 16S rDNA nucleotide divergence between two species of a genus were 0.21%, among genera of a subfamily were 0.42-3.38%, and among subfamilies of Pamphagidae were 1.90-8.88%, respectively. The phylogenetic tree shows that: 1) all Pamphagidae taxa form a monophyletic clade, and are well separated from the outgroup; 2) the African taxa Porthetinae (Lobosceliana brevicornis) and Akicerinae (Batrachotetrix sp.) are distinctly separated from the Chinese taxa Prionotropisinae; 3) Haplotropis bruneriana and Glauia terrea of Pamphaginae are nested in the middle of the tree, but their phylogenetic status is uncertain in this study; 4) 8 genera of Asiotmethis, Beybienkia, Mongolotmethis, Sinotmethis, Rhinotmethis, Filchnerella, Eotmethis and Pseudotmethis from China are all grouped into the subfamily Prionotropisinae, but their phylogenetic relationships are not clearly resolved.</abstract><indexing><discipline locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></discipline><subject locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></subject><subject_class locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></subject_class></indexing><author primary_contact="true"><firstname>D C</firstname><lastname>Zhang</lastname><email><![CDATA[]]></email></author><author primary_contact="false"><firstname>X J</firstname><lastname>Li</lastname><email><![CDATA[]]></email></author><author primary_contact="false"><firstname>W Q</firstname><lastname>Wang</lastname><email><![CDATA[]]></email></author><author primary_contact="false"><firstname>H</firstname><lastname>Yin</lastname><email><![CDATA[]]></email></author><author primary_contact="false"><firstname>Z</firstname><lastname>Yin</lastname><email><![CDATA[]]></email></author><author primary_contact="false"><firstname>X C</firstname><lastname>Yin</lastname><email><![CDATA[]]></email></author><pages>41-49</pages><date_published>2005-12-22</date_published></article><article language="en"><title locale="en_US">Revision of the genus Pseudomictis Hsiao and transfer of Pseudomictis quadrispinus to the genus Pternistria Stal (Hemiptera : Heteroptera : Coreidae : Coreinae : Mictini)</title><abstract locale="en_US">The genus Pseudomictis Hsiao and three known species, Pseudomictis brevicornis Hsiao, Pseudomictis distinctus Hsiao, and Pseudomictis obtusipinus Xiong, are examined, redescribed, and some of their characters not mentioned before are illustrated. One new species, Pseudomictis lativentralis Zhu et Bu, sp. nov., is described and illustrated. Pseudomictis quadrispinus Hsiao is transferred to the genus Pternistria as Pternistria quadrispinus (Hsiao), comb. nov., Keys to the genera of Chinese Mictini and to the species of Pseudomictis are included.</abstract><indexing><discipline locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></discipline><subject locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></subject><subject_class locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></subject_class></indexing><author primary_contact="true"><firstname>W B</firstname><lastname>Zhu</lastname><email><![CDATA[]]></email></author><author primary_contact="false"><firstname>W J</firstname><lastname>Bu</lastname><email><![CDATA[]]></email></author><pages>51-64</pages><date_published>2005-12-22</date_published></article></section></issue><issue current="false" identification="title" public_id="" published="true"><id type="doi">10.11646/zootaxa.1099.1</id><title locale="en_US">19 Dec. 2005</title><volume>1099</volume><number>1</number><year>2005</year><date_published>2005-12-19</date_published><section><title locale="en_US">Articles</title><article language="en"><title locale="en_US">Taxonomic review of the Tribe Melaenini (Coleoptera : Carabidae), with observations on morphological, ecological and chorological evolution</title><abstract locale="en_US">A taxonomic review of the tribe Melaenini (sensu novo), this paper includes a classification, keys at all taxonomic levels, descriptions (tribe to species), re-rankings, and new synonymy. In total, two genera and 22 species (three of which are new) are treated. Arrangement of taxa is in the following sequence, with junior synonyms and type localities of new species in parentheses, following name of the taxon. The Eastern Hemisphere genus Melaenus Dejean, 1831 includes M. piger (Fabricius, 1801), and M. elegans Dejean, 1831 (with M. elongatus Chaudoir, 1843, as a new junior synonym), which exhibits marked dimorphism in East Africa. The genus Cymbionotum Baudi di Selve, 1864 includes 20 species, arranged in two subgenera, as follows. The Western Hemisphere Procoscinia, n. subg. (type species, C. fernandezi, n. sp. Perrault, 1994. The Eastern Hemisphere subgenus Cymbionotum (sensu stricto) includes 18 species in three species groups, and three superspecies. The basale species group includes two species: C. semirubricum (Reitter, 1914) (new junior synonyms Graniger aethiopicus Alluaud, 1923, C. minax Andrewes, 1935, and C. a. airense Basilewsky, 1950), and C. basale (Dejean, 1831). The semelederi species group includes three species: C. semelederi (Chaudoir, 1851) (new junior synonyms, Coscinia funerula Fairmaire, 1885, Cymbionotum luniferum Andrewes 1935, and Graniger houskai Jedlicka, 1951), C. striatum Reitter, 1894, and C. mandli Jedli. ka, 1963. The schueppelii species group includes 13 species arrayed in three superspecies schueppelii superspecies, with three species: C. schueppelii (Dejean, 1825) (new junior synonym: C. capicola rufofasciatum Basilewsky, 1948), C. rufotestaceum (Fairmaire, 1893), and C. capicola (Peringuey, 1908); fasciatum superspecies, with five species: C. helferi (Chaudoir, 1850), C. fasciger (Chaudoir, 1852), C. fluviale Andrewes, 1935; C. pictulum (Bates, 1874), and C. fasciatum (Dejean, 1831) (new junior synonym: Graniger volkonskyi Colas, 1943); and microphthalmum superspecies, with five species: C. namwala, n. sp. (Namwala, Zambia), C. candidum Andrewes, 1935, C. subcaecum, n. sp. (Quetta, Pakistan), C. transcaspicum (Semenov, 1891) (new junior synonyms: Graniger rufotestaceus Pic, 1904 and G. mesopotamicus Csiki, 1929), and C. microphthalmum (Chaudoir, 1876). The taxonomic status of Graniger martini Bedel, 1908 remains doubtful, though it seems highly probable that it is conspecific with C. capicola (Peringuey), and is treated as such. The elongate diverticulum of the spermathecal gland establishesmonophyly of the Melaenini. Major postulates regarding structural evolution is that, of the two genera, most of the character states of Melaenus are ancestral relative to the character states of Cymbionotum. However, for Melaenus, loss of a pair of supraorbital setae and the posteriolateral pronotal setae, and gain of a transverse microsculpture mesh pattern, fimbriate sculpticells, and markedly convex elytral intervals are apotypic features. Many diagnostic character states of Cymbionotum are reductions or losses: body size, antennal length, elytral striae, metathoracic wing veins, parameral setae, endophallic sclerite x and rami of the ovipositor. Gains are: general body setation, and microtrichiate paraglossae. Within Cymbionotum, prominent changes are: color reduction (loss of melanin from the cuticle); reduction of eyes; reduction of antennomere 2; reduction and increase in setal density and gain and subsequent loss of the clypeal tooth; extension of the pronotum posteriad; and developent and subsequent loss of a beaded posterior margin of the pronotum. Ecologically, change was probably from rain forest tropical vegetation zone to dry forest, to grassland, marginally to desert/semi-desert, and at least one reversion to the rain forest vegetation zone. Altitudinal change was from lowland to highland. Chorologically, the most striking feature within the extant melaenines is evidence for pre-Cretaceous (or early Cretaceous) origin of both genera, and then evidence of Plio-Pleistocene differentiation from the many allopatric ranges of closely related species. But the distribution patterns provide no evidence about differentiation between the Cretaceous Period and Miocene Epoch. Each of the Neotropical, Afrotropical, Palaearctic, and Oriental Regions has two or more precinctive species, indicating that each region has provided one or more refugia, and hence the isolation required to make allopatric speciation possible.</abstract><indexing><discipline locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></discipline><subject locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></subject><subject_class locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></subject_class></indexing><author primary_contact="true"><firstname>G E</firstname><lastname>Ball</lastname><email><![CDATA[]]></email></author><author primary_contact="false"><firstname>D</firstname><lastname>Shpeley</lastname><email><![CDATA[]]></email></author><pages>1-120</pages><date_published>2005-12-19</date_published></article></section></issue><issue current="false" identification="title" public_id="" published="true"><id type="doi">10.11646/zootaxa.1101.1</id><title locale="en_US">19 Dec. 2005</title><volume>1101</volume><number>1</number><year>2005</year><date_published>2005-12-19</date_published><section><title locale="en_US">Articles</title><article language="en"><title locale="en_US">Catalogue of recent and fossil taxa of the family Architectonicidae Gray, 1850 ( Mollusca : Gastropoda)</title><abstract locale="en_US">The marine gastropod family Architectonicidae (= Solariidae), commonly known as sundials, comprises about 140 worldwide extant species classified in 11 genera. More than ten times as many names are used in the literature for both Recent and fossil taxa, the latter dating from the Mesozoic (Paleozoic taxa were misinterpreted). Herein we catalog more than 1550 names that have appeared in print at the family-group (10), genus-group (137), and species-group levels (1408). Of the last, nearly 1100 are found to be nomenclatorially available or potentially available. An Appendix is included in which nomenclatural changes are made and/or commented upon. It is demonstrated that Solarium maculatum Link, 1807 was validly introduced and, as Architectonica maculata (Link, 1807), becomes the valid name for the species usually cited as A. picta (Philippi, 1849). The invalid introduction of Heliacus messanensis Bertolaso &amp; Palazzi, 2000 is discussed. The emended spelling of the specific name in the binomen Solatisonax alleryi (G. Seguenza, 1876) is shown to be correctly accepted. Philippia lepida Bayer, 1942, Torinia gyrus depressiuscula Bayer, 1848, Solarium subconcolor von Martens, 1880, Solarium conulus Weinkauff, 1868 and Solarium submoniliferum d'Orbigny, 1852 were proposed as replacement names for multiple preoccupied names and/or misidentifications. These are here restricted to avoid possible confusion. The history and current status of the similarly spelled and inconsistently used nomina Fluxiella and Fluxinella (as placed in Architectonicidae and/or Seguenziidae) are discussed.</abstract><indexing><discipline locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></discipline><subject locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></subject><subject_class locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></subject_class></indexing><author primary_contact="true"><firstname>R</firstname><lastname>Bieler</lastname><email><![CDATA[]]></email></author><author primary_contact="false"><firstname>R E</firstname><lastname>Petit</lastname><email><![CDATA[]]></email></author><pages>1-119</pages><date_published>2005-12-19</date_published></article></section></issue><issue current="false" identification="title" public_id="" published="true"><id type="doi">10.11646/zootaxa.1098.1</id><title locale="en_US">19 Dec. 2005</title><volume>1098</volume><number>1</number><year>2005</year><date_published>2005-12-19</date_published><section><title locale="en_US">Articles</title><article language="en"><title locale="en_US">Whiteflies of Belize (Hemiptera : Aleyrodidae) Part 2 - A review of the subfamily aleyrodinae westwood</title><abstract locale="en_US">A field survey of Sternorrhyncha (Hemiptera) in Belize, principally conducted within the Chiquibul Forest Reserve (CFR), has revealed almost 200 species of whiteflies, all but 40 of them belonging to the subfamily Aleyrodinae. Provided here is an illustrated account of described Belize species of Aleyrodidae-Aleyrodinae. This account proposes three new generic synonymies, three new specific synonymies, nine ten combinations, one revalidated species and provides descriptions of three new genera and 12 new species. Two appendices are provided: a check list, which includes species remaining undescribed, and the associated host-plant genera or families (when known) of all putative species; and a summary of taxonomic changes proposed here. Line drawings and/or photographs of slide-mounted puparia are provided for all described species, and photographs alone are provided for a few of the more distinctive species that remain undescribed.</abstract><indexing><discipline locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></discipline><subject locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></subject><subject_class locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></subject_class></indexing><author primary_contact="true"><firstname>J H</firstname><lastname>Martin</lastname><email><![CDATA[]]></email></author><pages>1-116</pages><date_published>2005-12-19</date_published></article></section></issue><issue current="false" identification="title" public_id="" published="true"><id type="doi">10.11646/zootaxa.1102.1</id><title locale="en_US">19 Dec. 2005</title><volume>1102</volume><number>1</number><year>2005</year><date_published>2005-12-19</date_published><section><title locale="en_US">Articles</title><article language="en"><title locale="en_US">Catalogue of the superfamily Cancellarioidea Forbes and Hanley, 1851 (Gastropoda : Prosobranchia) - 2nd edition</title><abstract locale="en_US">This catalogue of cancellarioidean taxa is composed of three sections. The first lists alphabetically 124 genus-group taxa originally proposed or later included within the superfamily as well as 24 misspelled or nude names. The second section lists alphabetically 1,864 species-group names proposed in or subsequently referred to genera now considered to belong in Cancellarioidea. Also listed are 392 nude names, misspellings and incorrect attributions. The third section consists of a bibliography of works referred to in this paper.</abstract><indexing><discipline locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></discipline><subject locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></subject><subject_class locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></subject_class></indexing><author primary_contact="true"><firstname>R E</firstname><lastname>Petit</lastname><email><![CDATA[]]></email></author><author primary_contact="false"><firstname>M G</firstname><lastname>Harasewych</lastname><email><![CDATA[]]></email></author><pages>1-161</pages><date_published>2005-12-19</date_published></article></section></issue><issue current="false" identification="title" public_id="" published="true"><id type="doi">10.11646/zootaxa.1100.1</id><title locale="en_US">19 Dec. 2005</title><volume>1100</volume><number>1</number><year>2005</year><date_published>2005-12-19</date_published><section><title locale="en_US">Articles</title><article language="en"><title locale="en_US">The Middle American species of Embates Chevrolat (Coleoptera : Curculionidae : Baridinae)</title><abstract locale="en_US">The neotropical weevil genus Embates Chevrolat is revised. New synonyms of Embates are Drepanambates Jekel, Batames Casey, Macrambates Casey and Cholinambates Casey. Information is provided about the morphology of the immature stages, life history, sexual dimorphism and morphological variability. A total of 69 species is recognized in Middle America, 38 of which are newly described here: E. aequiperabilis, E. aliquantulus, E. bicoctura, E. burgeri, E. callifer, E. chelys, E. clandestinus, E. consimilis, E. cordiger, E. crinipes, E. discissus, E. discordabilis, E. euchasma, E. euscheme, E. flavoplagiatus, E. galbinus, E. gilvopictus, E. gracilis, E. intermedius, E. kunicus, E. maculifer, E. marchionis, E. mendax, E. oculifer, E. paludicola, E. paucilimbatus, E. pauhans, E. peperomiae, E. politus, E. pseudobumbraticus, E. pullus, E. rutilus, E. sagittifolicus, E. scambus, E. subulirostris, E. terrabanicus, E. todillofasciatus and E. uniformis. Six new subspecies are described: E. polymorphus altrimsecus, E. polymorphus dotensis, E. polymorphus fortunensis, E. polymorphus tabulensis, E. polymorphus zeledonensis and E. leucopleura discolor. New combinations are E. belti (Champion), E. leucopleura (Champion) and E. flavolimbatus (Voss) [all from Drepanambates]. New synonyms are E. belti [= E. triangularis (Champion)], E. fasciolatus (Chevrolat) [= E. sexpunctatus (Champion)] and E. solani (Champion) [= E. divisus (Casey)]. Embates rugosus (Hustache) is distinguished from E. solani and resurrected as a valid species. New records for Middle America are E. flavolimbatus (Voss), E. justini (Chevrolat) and E. rugosus. Descriptions, line drawings of habitus and male genitalia, geographic distributions, plant associations and keys for identification are provided.</abstract><indexing><discipline locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></discipline><subject locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></subject><subject_class locale="en_US"><![CDATA[]]></subject_class></indexing><author primary_contact="true"><firstname>J</firstname><lastname>Prena</lastname><email><![CDATA[]]></email></author><pages>1-151</pages><date_published>2005-12-19</date_published></article></section></issue></issues>